<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>intsvy | Byoung-gyu Gong</title>
    <link>/tag/intsvy/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/intsvy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>intsvy</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>intsvy</title>
      <link>/tag/intsvy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why is PISA Difficult to Analyze (Lesson.One)</title>
      <link>/post/why-pisa-is-difficult-to-analyze/why-is-the-pisa-data-hard-to-analyze/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/why-pisa-is-difficult-to-analyze/why-is-the-pisa-data-hard-to-analyze/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;By Byoung-gyu Gong&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/Why-PISA-is-difficult-to-analyze/featured.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-ilsa-and-pisa&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is ILSA and PISA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;International large-scale assessment (ILSA) is conducted regularly by the international organizations to measure and compare educational performance and status of many different countries. Among many others, Programme for International Student Assessment (PISA) by OECD is the most well-known ILSA testing member and non-member partner country’s 15-year-old students every two years. It measures students’ reading, math, and science using computer-based instrument. It also surveys to collect more detailed background information of each student, teacher, and school. The PISA 2006 collected these massive size of data from 398,750 students. Thus, it can be said that the PISA is the most comprehensive large sized international students assessment data set available now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-is-it-difficult-to-analyze-pisa-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Why is it difficult to analyze PISA data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of insightful knowledge we can gain from this large international students’ data set, PISA is not easily accessible to most of the researchers to analyze it. That is not because the access to the data is limited but rather because the data is complexly structured requesting sophisticated data pre-processing. Even Jerrim, Lopez-Agudo, Marcenaro-Gutierrez, and Shure (2017) said “in spite of their acquired relevance, there are few studies which really account for the complex survey and test designs that they present and follow the technical procedures suggested by their developers” (p.1). I will illustrate what caution needed to analyze the data set and provides R solution in this post using data set of PISA 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;two-staged-sampling&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1. Two-staged sampling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sampling design of the PISA is the reason why the analysis procedure is so complicated. The PISA does not use random sampling and instead follows two staged sampling: firstly sample schools and then sample students in the participating schools. This makes the sampling errors of population estimates increase. It conflicts with most of the computer softwares designed to assume random sampling for statistical analysis, and requests more sophisticated analysis procedure. Once the assumption of random sampling is violated, the student data can be dependent on each other because they may share common school characteristics.&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid such bias, PISA made some complementary measures.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you look at the data table imported from the PISA 2006, you would see a number of strange variable names such as PV1-5 for each reading, math, and science domains. Also, there are a number of variables having names like W_FSTR1-80. If you just naively wanted to calculate students’ mean or correlation coefficient with a fixed point score, you would be embarrased to find these strange variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;head(pisa2006,1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   X CNT SCHOOLID STIDSTD  PV1MATH  PV2MATH  PV3MATH  PV4MATH  PV5MATH  PV1READ
## 1 1 ARG        1       1 305.1799 305.9589 264.6752 320.7587 301.2852 357.0519
##    PV2READ  PV3READ  PV4READ  PV5READ  PV1SCIE  PV2SCIE  PV3SCIE  PV4SCIE
## 1 312.1348 281.6554 316.9474 316.1453 395.3131 411.1652 445.6667 351.4869
##    PV5SCIE  PV1INTR  PV2INTR  PV3INTR  PV4INTR  PV5INTR  PV1SUPP  PV2SUPP
## 1 356.1492 539.9939 480.1177 497.9912 370.1956 506.0343 339.0228 395.3084
##    PV3SUPP  PV4SUPP  PV5SUPP   PV1EPS   PV2EPS   PV3EPS   PV4EPS   PV5EPS
## 1 412.5387 313.7517 322.9412 393.4482 384.1234 354.2843 430.7471 417.6925
##     PV1ISI   PV2ISI   PV3ISI   PV4ISI   PV5ISI   PV1USE  PV2USE   PV3USE
## 1 334.7023 304.8632 323.5126 399.9755 386.9209 401.8404 383.191 385.0559
##    PV4USE  PV5USE W_FSTUWT W_FSTR1  W_FSTR2 W_FSTR3  W_FSTR4 W_FSTR5  W_FSTR6
## 1 436.342 469.911  98.8278 52.1041 139.9112 52.1041 139.9112 52.1041 139.9112
##   W_FSTR7 W_FSTR8 W_FSTR9 W_FSTR10 W_FSTR11 W_FSTR12 W_FSTR13 W_FSTR14 W_FSTR15
## 1 52.1041 52.1041 52.1041  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112
##   W_FSTR16 W_FSTR17 W_FSTR18 W_FSTR19 W_FSTR20 W_FSTR21 W_FSTR22 W_FSTR23
## 1  52.1041  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112  52.1041
##   W_FSTR24 W_FSTR25 W_FSTR26 W_FSTR27 W_FSTR28 W_FSTR29 W_FSTR30 W_FSTR31
## 1 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112  52.1041  52.1041  52.1041  52.1041 139.9112
##   W_FSTR32 W_FSTR33 W_FSTR34 W_FSTR35 W_FSTR36 W_FSTR37 W_FSTR38 W_FSTR39
## 1 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112  52.1041  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112
##   W_FSTR40 W_FSTR41 W_FSTR42 W_FSTR43 W_FSTR44 W_FSTR45 W_FSTR46 W_FSTR47
## 1 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112  52.1041
##   W_FSTR48 W_FSTR49 W_FSTR50 W_FSTR51 W_FSTR52 W_FSTR53 W_FSTR54 W_FSTR55
## 1  52.1041  52.1041  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112
##   W_FSTR56 W_FSTR57 W_FSTR58 W_FSTR59 W_FSTR60 W_FSTR61 W_FSTR62 W_FSTR63
## 1  52.1041  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112  52.1041
##   W_FSTR64 W_FSTR65 W_FSTR66 W_FSTR67 W_FSTR68 W_FSTR69 W_FSTR70 W_FSTR71
## 1 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112  52.1041  52.1041  52.1041  52.1041 139.9112
##   W_FSTR72 W_FSTR73 W_FSTR74 W_FSTR75 W_FSTR76 W_FSTR77 W_FSTR78 W_FSTR79
## 1 139.9112  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112  52.1041  52.1041 139.9112 139.9112
##   W_FSTR80    ESCS
## 1 139.9112 -2.0048&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, what are these variables in the PISA table?
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;sampling-weight&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2. Sampling Weight&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make each sampled student from each school represent entire population of each country, we need to give a weight to each student variables. The random sample secures equal probability of each sampled student, but two-stage sampling needs to adjust the probability with complicated calculation of the weight. Weight is an inverse of probability to be selected as sample. For instance, we selected 10 students out of total 100 students, then the probability to be selected is 0.1 and weight is 10.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In PISA each a probability of each school to be selected is proportional to its size, which is called PPS sampling method. Then, the schools with larger size has a higher probability of selection, but the students in the larger schools have proportionally less within-school probability of selection. Also, the sum of students’ weight for each country is the total number of the students’ population assumed for the study.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two options to apply students’ weight for the PISA analysis, applying final weight, and replicated weight, but in this post, I don’t tackle with the replicated weight because it is more related to the estimation of standard error but not for other estimates.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me show you an example here with R code. W_FSTUWT is the final students’ weight. You can see that students in the same school has approximately the same school weights with a little variation. School number 00001 has weights around 98, and 00002 has it at about 89.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Select Argentina students&amp;#39; weight information.
WEIGHT&amp;lt;-pisa2006 %&amp;gt;% select(CNT, SCHOOLID, W_FSTUWT) %&amp;gt;% filter(CNT==&amp;quot;ARG&amp;quot;)
# Create a dataframe that can compare Argentina students in three different schools
A&amp;lt;-WEIGHT %&amp;gt;% filter(SCHOOLID==&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% slice(1:3)
B&amp;lt;-WEIGHT %&amp;gt;% filter(SCHOOLID==&amp;quot;2&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% slice(1:3)
C&amp;lt;-WEIGHT %&amp;gt;% filter(SCHOOLID==&amp;quot;3&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% slice(1:3)
rbind(A,B,C)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   CNT SCHOOLID W_FSTUWT
## 1 ARG        1  98.8278
## 2 ARG        1  91.7075
## 3 ARG        1  98.8278
## 4 ARG        2  89.3573
## 5 ARG        2  89.6970
## 6 ARG        2  89.6970
## 7 ARG        3 112.7806
## 8 ARG        3 117.0837
## 9 ARG        3 117.0837&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
The summation of the students’ weight is equal to the population, total population of 15-years-old students in Argentina. It is 523,047.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;WEIGHT %&amp;gt;% filter(CNT==&amp;quot;ARG&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% group_by(CNT) %&amp;gt;% summarize(sum=sum(W_FSTUWT))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## `summarise()` ungrouping output (override with `.groups` argument)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 1 x 2
##   CNT       sum
##   &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;   &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
## 1 ARG   523048.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, we can compare difference in variable means between raw scores and weighted scores. Comparing with the graph ‘B’ with the graph ‘A’, we can recognize that the graph ‘B’ is more slighted deviated from the regression line although for most of the countries the difference is negligible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ESCS is the socio-economic status (SES) index
# Create weighted mean score (W_MEAN) and non-weighted means score of ESCS
# Calculate national mean
PV1SCIE&amp;lt;-pisa2006 %&amp;gt;% select(CNT, PV1SCIE, W_FSTUWT) %&amp;gt;% group_by(CNT) %&amp;gt;%  mutate(W_MEAN=weighted.mean(PV1SCIE,W_FSTUWT, na.rm=TRUE), MEAN=mean(PV1SCIE, na.rm=TRUE)) %&amp;gt;% ungroup() %&amp;gt;% select(CNT, W_MEAN, MEAN) %&amp;gt;% unique()

# Create a scatter plot to compare the discrepancy between 
library(ggplot2)
library(ggpubr)
# Create a scatter plot with raw score means (unweighted mean)
Non_weight&amp;lt;-ggplot(PV1SCIE, aes(x=MEAN, y=MEAN)) + geom_point() + geom_text(data=PV1SCIE, aes(label=CNT), position=position_jitter(width=0.1,height=0.1), size=3) + geom_smooth(method=lm, se=TRUE)+stat_cor(method = &amp;quot;pearson&amp;quot;)
# Create a scatter plot with unweighted mean and weighted mean
Weight_non_weight&amp;lt;-ggplot(PV1SCIE, aes(x=MEAN, y=W_MEAN)) + geom_point() + geom_text(data=PV1SCIE, aes(label=CNT), position=position_jitter(width=0.1,height=0.1), size=3) + geom_smooth(method=lm, se=TRUE)+stat_cor(method = &amp;quot;pearson&amp;quot;)
# Compore these two
ggarrange(Non_weight, Weight_non_weight, 
          labels = c(&amp;quot;A&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;B&amp;quot;),
          ncol = 2, nrow = 1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## `geom_smooth()` using formula &amp;#39;y ~ x&amp;#39;
## `geom_smooth()` using formula &amp;#39;y ~ x&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/Why-PISA-is-difficult-to-analyze/2020-10-10-why-is-the-pisa-data-hard-to-analyze.en_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;plausible-valuepv&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3. Plausible Value(PV)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PV is called plausible value and each domain has five PVs. For instance, math has PV1MATH - PV5MATH and science has PV1SCIE - PV5SCIE. The PVs are introduced here to adjust measurement error that can be caused by (1) the concept to be measured is not clear, (2) students physical and psychological condition affected on the moment of testing, and (3) the testing environment on a day of testing. Thus, if we have five different plausible values distributed in the certain range of raw score, we can avoid point estimate of the students’ competency which has high risk of measurement error as mentioned above. This means that we interpret students’ competency as a probability distribution among the plausible values not as a fixed point. In addition to this rational, the PV was adopted in a practical and efficiency stand point. In PISA tests, students do not take all the test items as it is time consuming and each student take different set of test, while the test items missing in each students are treated as missing value. This creates five different set of literally plausible score value of the students.
 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I created two columns of mean data to compare between weighted PV means and weighted means of each country. However, as we can see from the below table, there is not much significant difference between weighted PV mean and just weighted mean with the final weight. The OECD also admitted that PV value does not bring significant impact to reduce bias in estimate (OECD, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Create a dataframe with weighted PV means (weighted by final weight)
PVSCIE&amp;lt;-pisa.mean.pv(pvlabel=&amp;quot;SCIE&amp;quot;, by=&amp;quot;CNT&amp;quot;, data=pisa2006)
# Create a dataframe with weighted means (weighted by final weight)
SCIE&amp;lt;-pisa2006 %&amp;gt;% group_by(CNT) %&amp;gt;% summarise(Mean=(weighted.mean(PV4SCIE,W_FSTUWT, na.rm=TRUE))) %&amp;gt;% mutate(Mean=round(Mean, 2))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## `summarise()` ungrouping output (override with `.groups` argument)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Merge&amp;lt;-left_join(PVSCIE, SCIE, by=&amp;quot;CNT&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;% select(CNT, Freq, Mean.x, Mean.y) %&amp;gt;% rename(PVmean=&amp;quot;Mean.x&amp;quot;, Rawmean=&amp;quot;Mean.y&amp;quot;)
head(Merge,15)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##    CNT  Freq PVmean Rawmean
## 1  ARG  4339 391.24  391.33
## 2  AUS 14170 526.88  526.90
## 3  AUT  4927 510.84  510.95
## 4  AZE  5184 382.33  381.78
## 5  BEL  8857 510.36  510.62
## 6  BGR  4498 434.08  433.27
## 7  BRA  9295 390.33  389.43
## 8  CAN 22646 534.47  534.28
## 9  CHE 12192 511.52  511.71
## 10 CHL  5233 438.18  438.26
## 11 COL  4478 388.04  388.60
## 12 CZE  5932 512.86  512.69
## 13 DEU  4891 515.65  516.32
## 14 DNK  4532 495.89  495.05
## 15 ESP 19604 488.42  487.51&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerrim, J., Lopez-Agudo, L. A., Marcenaro-Gutierrez, O. D., &amp;amp; Shure, N. (2017, June). To weight or not to weight?: the case of PISA data. In Proceedings of the XXVI Meeting of the Economics of Education Association, Murcia, Spain (pp. 29-30).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OECD (2009). PISA 2006 Technical Report. OECD Publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
